[Music]
good evening and good day everyone
welcome to episode 18 of ask abhijit
today is the astrophysics space and
universe special
i hope you're doing well so and as
always you have asked many very
interesting questions
so let's start with the questions right
away
and question number one is a very good
question
in which direction did the big bang
happen
so this is a question i believe that all
kids would have all
new students of physics would have about
the big bang theory i'm sure i must have
had this question when i was a kid
and this is a question that no teacher
essentially answers
they discourage you from asking
questions and that's why this question
remains with us for the
for the remainder of our lives so
in what direction did the big bang
happen so let's understand what this big
bang
was so according to the best theory of
the universe that we have the so-called
big bang theory
the universe began as an extremely
compact and extremely small
point just one small point
in finite decimal is small all the mass
and energy of the universe was
concentrated in that point
and it expanded from that so it's not an
explosion it's an expansion
what is the difference between the two
an explosion is something that happens
in one place
like a cracker bursting or a grenade
blast
so it is something that happens in one
place and it ejects
material in all directions so if the big
bang
was an explosion of the universe you
would find bits and pieces of the
universe being
thrown out in different directions
that's not the case
the universe is just one it's one single
entity
so it was a very rapid expansion and
incredibly humongously
ridiculously rapid expansion so that's
what happened
so that was the big bang and
the universe expanded super luminally
which means it expanded
the faster than the speed of light so
that's why it looks like an expansion
like an explosion that's why this
colloquial term big bang has been used
for it
so because of the way the universe
expanded it means that
every single place every single
location in the universe was once
concentrated in that small
little singularity or near singularity
which means that the big bang happened
everywhere everything was part of the
big bang
where i am sitting right now it was part
of that initial
extremely condensed extremely small
state
in in which the universe existed and
wherever you're sitting right now there
was also part of it
what this means is that it is not
incorrect
in any way to say that the big bang
happened everywhere
all of the space time that we have
around us today that we are inside
was part of this initial expansion of
the universe
so the big bang basically was the entire
universe
and therefore it happened at all places
at the same time it happened here
it happened where you are it happened
where jupiter is it happened at the
andromeda galaxy
it happened in the farthest galaxy super
cluster that we can observe
etc everything was part of it so there
is no actual direction
everything was inside that little
tiny infinitesimally small point
that was the very early
universe so that's how it is so i hope
that answers your question it clarifies
your
question to some extent hopefully
avinash again asks the same a different
question why did the big bang
take place that's another very good
question
so the best theory like i said that we
have
of the universe is the so called big
bang
theory now what does this theory say
first of all what
is this theory this theory
is a model of the history of the
universe
this is the best theory that we have and
it's a model
of the history of our universe after the
big bang
occurred it is not a theory
of the creation of the universe
that's what we have to understand
there's a big difference the big bang
theory is not a theory of the
creation of the universe it is a model
of the history
of the universe after the big bang took
place and after the very early
period of the universe's history which
we don't really understand very well
so around 10 raised to see so basically
the universe had a birthday
the universe there was a point in time
so to say
before which there was no yesterday in
the universe
so the universe emerged at a certain
time it was a
well at a certain time you can say that
yeah but before that there was no time
so the universe had a birthday and
everything proceeds further
in a certain direction of time from that
point onwards
so when the universe was about 10 raised
to minus 36 seconds
old it was about the size of of a
of a tennis ball or cricket ball or an
apple
so we begin to understand the big bang
theory
essentially begins to understand the
universe from that point onwards
because before that you had grand
unification which we don't quite
understand
so before that point basically all four
forces that
we know of in nature the strong nuclear
force the weak nuclear force
electromagnetism and gravitation these
were all
of equal strength gravity's role was
much more
uh prominent at that time right it was
as strong as the other forces
and afterwards the forces decoupled into
the in
become similar to what we experienced
today
so our understanding of the old
of the early universe proceeds forward
from that point onwards
from 10 raised to minus 36 seconds
onwards and it's an approximate
understanding of how things occurred so
basically the big bang theory is a model
of
what happened from that point onwards it
is it doesn't seek to explain it is not
able to explain what caused the initial
expansion itself
so you go you go and ask any scientist
any theoretical physicist
in the world they will not be able to
answer why did the big bang take place
what caused it what triggered the
initial
expansion of the universe what triggered
the creation of the universe
we don't know so this these are the
limitations that we
currently have in our understanding of
the universe and
and in our understanding of science
itself of the laws of nature itself
so there's a great deal to understand
there's a great deal that we don't know
so that's what i keep emphasizing that
there is so much to
that's why physics theoretical physics
and physical cosmology
and astrophysics that's why it's so
interesting it's so fascinating because
there is so much still
left to understand so much still left to
discover
the history of the very early universe
is an especially fascinating
topic because it basically talks about
grand unification
which is the so-called so-called holy
grail of physics
the unification of the four four forces
of nature and any others if any others
do exist
so so basically that's your answer we do
not know what
triggered the big bang what laws or what
what
uh forces or what it was that triggered
this this event
we don't know we only understand what
happened after a certain point
in the very early history of the
universe and that too it's an
approximate understanding
there are still many uh many many uh
data points that we don't have and many
things we still don't understand
but it is the best theory that we have
as of now and it it does explain
a lot about the universe and we do have
a lot of evidence that supports this
theory
so that's your answer sir
avinash again asks what is it like
inside a black hole so
what we understand about black holes
comes from the theory of general
relativity
and this theory says that when you take
a mass any mass and you compress it
further and further the effect it has on
space-time becomes more and more acute
so if if space time is a sheet and a
ball
of mass produces produces this
distortion in the field
in the sheet then the more condensed
masses the more the more dense a mass is
the greater it's going to stretch the
fabric of space-time
and if you compress a mass sufficiently
enough
so that it becomes equal to or less than
its
so-called schwarzschild radius then it
basically
produces an infinite amount of
warping of this fabric of space-time and
that's what we call a black hole
so the equations of general relativity
einstein's equations
they produce what's called a singularity
which means it's division by zero
it doesn't mean that there's an actual
infinite density in there
it actually means that our theory isn't
able to handle that possible
that that specific condition it means
our theory isn't
accurate enough it it it shows up the
limitations
of the theory of general relativity it
tells you that we need to
be able to formulate a better theory we
need to formulate a better theory one
that
takes into account account the
the quantum uh domain of the universe so
we basically need to
find a way to reconcile quantum
mechanics quantum field theory
and general relativity which is
something we haven't achieved
thus far because if you try to quantize
gravity it doesn't work it grow it blows
up
it breaks down uh you cannot have
space i mean you cannot have quantum
fields here it doesn't work in curved
space
time etc so these are the problems that
theoretical physicists are grappling
with
so essentially what i'm trying to say in
so many words
is we don't know what's inside a black
hole a black hole is something that's
it's a region of space-time that's cut
off
completely from outside orbit of from
outside observers
the boundary is what's called the event
horizon
and there is no way of knowing what's
inside because everything that goes
inside never comes out
except in the form of thermal radiation
the so-called hoaxing radiation
which doesn't tell you anything about
what's really inside the
the black hole so what's inside a black
hole
we don't know there could be well
there are speculations the black hole be
could possibly be a bag of
single dimensional strings perhaps
it could be something that contains just
radiation
photons maybe it contains just pure mass
that's another speculation or
possibility some people say that a
supermassive black hole
could or any black hole could
essentially be a pathway to a different
universe
it could end on the other side in a
white hole and and bring you out in a
different universe
in which time flows backwards and then
it's
it's also a possibility that
supermassive black holes may contain
entire universes inside them
so these are speculations but we have no
way of knowing
first of all because we don't have
access to a black hole on which we can
do experiments
because you know what black holes do
they they suck everything in in
so we don't have access to a black hole
in a laboratory we don't have any
black hole that anywhere nearby us that
we that we can observe
and and get a better idea of
and the theoretical framework that we
have
isn't able to explain or answer these
questions of what is the internal
structure of a
black hole we know that black holes have
mass they have charge they have angular
momentum and basically these are the
three things
that uh characterize the properties of a
black hole we don't know much beyond
that
so there is a great deal of research
happening into the
this very much into this this matter
but as of today this is another example
of the limitations
of our understanding of nature we don't
know what is the internal structure of a
black hole we don't know what's inside
we don't know what's beyond
so it's a great question and these are
the questions that drive
physics forward
abi asks greeting from greetings from
poland greetings greetings sir
is it possible that all the things in
the universe including our solar system
earth and living non-living things are
all inside the brain
of some other living being where we all
live well
that's interesting there's this uh
theory it's a
it's a philosophical theory it's called
cosmopsychism which says that the
universe
is essentially conscious in itself which
would indicate it's a brain of some kind
and it's interesting that if you look at
the large-scale
structure of the universe at the largest
scales the filamentary structure of the
universe
where you have filaments of which are
made up of galaxy superclusters and
these filaments connect the
various regions of the universe together
if you look at the filamentary structure
of the universe at the largest scales
it is almost exactly the same as the
neural structure of our brain
yeah so so that is something that is
very striking and it's
something many people have noticed and
commented about
but the thing is that in our brain uh
signals
travel at the speed of nearly at the
speed of light the neural
signals are not quite at the speed of
light but these are electrical signals
that that are transmitted between
neurons
and clusters via electrochemical
processes using various ions and all
that
so these are biochemical processes that
transmit uh
what we interpret as our thoughts and
various signals inside the brain
so in the universe if the universe were
a brain and it were
if it were actually transmitting
thoughts to various different
regions then that transmission process
is limited by the speed of light so it
would typically take several
million years from a signal to be
transmitted from one location in this
filament
to another to a different location in
the filament because that's how large
these filaments are
so that is one of the big limitations in
this theory
that if it was a thinking brain then the
thought process would be incredibly slow
maybe the thought process was would be
on the order of the
uh of the age of the universe or
thereabouts because the universe is so
vast
maybe it's a very slow thinking brain or
maybe there is something that
circumvents this limit or and then
bypasses this limit maybe there are
actually wormholes in the universe that
we don't know about
and maybe these wormholes if maybe if
they are made of cosmic strings
possibly perhaps then maybe these
wormholes are
able to transmit thoughts faster than
the speed of light and transmit signals
faster than the speed of light
so these this is all hypothetical it's
all theoretical
but but the large scale structure of the
universe does very closely resemble the
neural structure of the brain
so it's an interesting thought uh there
is no evidence of this yeah it is a
is it possibly possible but it's not a
scientific theory because we don't have
observational evidence of any
signals being being transmitted right so
it's a it's a theory which belongs in
the realm of philosophy not science
philosophy is something that's
larger than science science is a small
subset of philosophy
so this is a philosophical theory until
we find any evidence
of this it is going to remain a
philosophical theory if we do actually
find some evidence then we can
bring it into the realm of science and
do some actual experimental uh
testing or or try and find some data
some actual
hard data about it so is it possible
maybe it's possible
it does the structure of the universe
does resemble the structure
the internal structure of the human
brain so it's it's very tantalizing it's
a good question
it's something even i've thought about
in the past but as i said we don't have
sufficient or or any credible data that
supports this this claim as of today
meenakshi asks why does every galaxy
have a black hole
at its center does this explain the
theory that the universe is a hologram
projected by hawking's radiation called
carrying quantum data from the event
horizon
yeah okay so let me answer why does
every galaxy have a black hole at its
center
you are right uh most galaxies that we
know of
are known to have a supermassive black
hole at their
centers so how so why is it so
how did this come about so it is uh
the the leading theory for this is that
in the very early universe you had
quantum fluctuations
which are basically a feature of quantum
field theory the entire
empty space is not empty it's teaming
with quantum fluctuations
particle anti-particle pairs popping in
and out of existence
in a very short time frame etc so
so in the early in the extremely early
universe too you had this quantum
fluctuations
and the universe was so dense like i
said at that time in the very early
uh phase that these quantum fluctuations
would possibly have
caused regions of spatial
over densities which would call which
would cause
microscopic black holes to be formed
so it is possible that the early
universe saw the birth of an
incredibly large amount an abundance of
microscopic black holes
and it is theorized that it is these
that where the seeds of future galaxies
so as the universe expanded and cooled
these black holes depending on the size
remained uh remained a feature of the
universe that spread across the universe
and it is around these black holes these
micro black holes or primordial black
holes that the first collections of
matter
began to form and these eventually
became galaxies
and over time these black holes absorbed
a significant portion of the galactic
mass
and they slowly uh became larger and
eventually became supermassive in size
so that is the leading theory as of
today as to why every galaxy has
almost every galaxy that we know of has
a supermassive black hole at the center
so these were possibly
see these probably originated as
primordial black hole seeds like small
seeds that grow into something larger
and larger
over the eons over the over the billions
of years of the universe's uh lifespan
so that is a very that is the leading
theories of now and
these primordial black holes are a very
interesting concept because they could
possibly possibly be part of
a significant fraction of the dark
matter of the universe dark matter is
something we still don't have an answer
to
so primordial black holes or primordial
black hole binaries for example or some
other configuration
could possibly be a component of the
missing dark matter of the universe
so it's a it's it's a theory that has a
great deal of currency
people are searching for primordial
black holes but
thus far we haven't found any evidence
or signature
of those black holes people's people
search for the
scientists are searching for the uh
hawking radiation bursts that a dying
primordial black hole would give off
thus far we haven't found it it doesn't
mean that it doesn't exist these things
don't exist
maybe they exist in a different form
maybe they have
maybe they have formed binaries of some
kind and they've become stable in some
manner
we don't know as of now but it's uh it's
one of the
uh one of the leading theories
in in physics in the field of dark
matter as well as
as as an explanation for these
supermassive black holes that we find at
the center
of almost every galaxy we know of so i
hope that answers
your question
okay pink line how how are space
and time correlated with each other
i asked this to my physics teacher but
she replied
that the question does not does not make
any sense please clear this doubt
well it's unfortunate that your teacher
said this i will not make any
pass any judgment about your teacher
but this question makes a lot of sense
it does make a lot of sense these are
the questions
that that basically help us understand
physics better
these questions should be encouraged and
these questions should be answered
this is an intelligent question right
so as we know we talk about space time
the fabric of space time so what is
space time and how are space and time
correlated
so the world that we observe in our
daily life in our mundane day-to-day
existence
is a three-dimensional world we
experience the world in three dimensions
length breadth and height right we don't
think of time as a dimension and we
don't see any way in which it is related
to the length
breadth and height of the world that we
live in
and yet according to general relativity
which is one of the most successful
theories that we have it actually works
so according to this theory
the universe is actually a four
dimensional stage
in which everything exists and time is
the fourth dimension it is intrinsically
linked with the other three spatial
dimensions the three dimension of space
and the one dimension of time are all
linked together in this composite fabric
of space-time
so the question like you're saying is
what is the relation between time
and space how are they together and let
me answer that question
the easiest and simplest and best way to
understand
the correlation of time and space is to
understand how
matter affects time and space
so we know that matter warps space
right in general relativity and in the
same way matter affects
time too so if you look at the
four-dimensional fabric of space-time as
a sheet
like like everyone does and if you place
a massive ball or any massive object in
it
it's going to warp this fabric it warps
not just
space but time too so mass affects space
and time equally so what does it do in
in in space it warps space and this
warping of space is what we perceive as
the force of gravity
and similarly it changes the way time
flows as well so it is an effect on both
space and time
so the presence of a mass essentially
gives you the effect of
slowing down time if you're standing on
the surface of the earth
of the planet time flows at a certain
speed
if you go up in a spacecraft let's say
100 kilometers or 500 kilometers above
the earth
time will flow slightly fractionally
faster we can actually
measure this with very precise atomic
clocks
so that's what is the correlation
between space and time
both are affected equally by the
presence of
mass and the larger the mass the more
visible is the effect
so if we were to take uh do an orbit
around a black hole without being sucked
into it and then if you were to move
away
you would find that a great deal of time
has passed it may feel like half an hour
for you
but for an outside observer who is far
away
it may be 50 or 60 years or even a
century
so that the way time passes for you near
a massive object
is very different from the way time
passes for somebody else who is far away
from that massive object
so this is the effect that mass has uh
oh yeah mass has
on space and time both and that is the
correlation
between space and time when you see it
in the in the context of
general relativity it is very hard to
see this difference
on a planet like like the earth because
we only see the same reality all of us
we are all
stuck in this on the surface of a very
small planet and we know nothing else
it's only when you go beyond the planet
into space
or if you go near a massive object which
we still don't have access to
yeah so it's only in those situations
when you actually that you actually see
the effect
that gravity has on space and time both
so time would
flow much slower if you go in an orbit
around the sun
for example maybe it would cut off a few
seconds you know
or something like that you can actually
calculate these things with
uh the laws of lots of special
relativity
right so that is the correlation between
space and time that's the easiest way to
express the correlation
between space and time they are part of
the same fabric and they are both
affected by the presence of mass
i hope that throws some light on the
matter i hope that inspires you to
actually study general relativity
and find out the actual mathematics that
causes this because it is the
mathematics that actually clarifies this
i'm just giving you when you when you
communicate these
these complex topics it's there is
always some something that's lost in
translation
the best way to understand this is to
actually study the math
that is the language of physics but that
is
uh it's a labor of love because you
learn that math the math can be quite
tough
the math of general relativity takes
some time getting used to tensor
calculus tensor algebra all that but it
is worthwhile if you if you really uh
have a passion for it so i hope that
answers your question
at least uh at least uh
at a late person's perspective
okay atheist asks what actually is
multiplication
it is not repeated is it not
repeated addition and what does the
multiplication
in f equals m multiplied by a mean
well you are right uh multiplication is
nothing but repeated addition
if we say 2 times 10 is 20 you're
basically adding 2
10 times so that is the simple thing
about multiplication it is nothing but
repeated addition that's how little
children are taught you start adding it
together
and that's how you get an intuitive
understanding of
what multiplication is at least if
you're if you're teaching a child
properly then that's how you explain it
to them
so it becomes intuitive uh what does the
multiplication
in f equals m multiplied by a mean so
what
this equation that you've shown over
here f equals m a
it is it expresses the newton's second
law of motion right
it says what it says is that the
acceleration
produced on a mass is proportional to
the force that's applied on the mass
and these are vector quantities
acceleration has a direction
and so is the force now what is this is
this multiplication what is it so let's
break this equation down f is
it represents force m represents mass
a represents acceleration now
in this equation m is a constant every
body has
in newtonian physics a constant mass
so this equation is basically to be
understood in the context of a
constant mass and when you see
m as a constant this equation becomes an
equation of proportionality
it says that mass and it says that
acceleration and force are proportional
to each other
and the proportionality is dependent on
the
amount of mass that the body has let's
let's break it down further
let's say i have a mass i have an object
that has
one kilogram of mass it's it its mass is
one kilogram
and let's say i apply a force to this
object
which produces an acceleration of one
meter per second squared
okay one kilogram mass and i
apply a force to this object which
produces an acceleration of one meter
per second square so f equals one
kilogram
times one meter per second square which
is one newton which is the
which is the unit of force
so if the mass was 2 then f would be 2
newtons if the mass was 10 kilograms
and i'm applying a force that causes an
acceleration of 1 kilogram one
meter per second square then the force
is 10 newtons
so that is a proportionality so this
equation
expresses the proportionality between
force
and acceleration and the resultant
acceleration
so that's newton's second law of motion
and
so it's a very good question this is how
you clarify these topics
right this is this is proportionality
and it's a vector
proportionality i will not go into what
vectors are vectors are directional
quantities
so acceleration is something that
happens in a specific direction it
doesn't happen in all directions
and forces too the resultant force on
a body is usually is is always in one
direction forces may come from
the resultant force may be the sum total
of many different forces many
different directions but the sum total
is always in one specific direction
and that is the direction in which the
acceleration also takes place
so i hope that clarifies and you can
study that further
if you look up newton's second law of
motion
akash asks is elon musk capable of
nuking the polls of mars is it a good
idea
so i think he has been saying this let's
nuke mars let's nuke mars i think he's
saying this
in a humorous vein uh i don't think
i don't think he's serious about it it's
just a joke uh
is he capable of nuking mars he doesn't
have access to nuclear weapons no
civilian on this planet
has access to nuclear weapons nuclear
weapons are closely guarded
they are guarded very closely and with a
great deal of military security right
these are the
most dangerous weapons that we have so
this is something only government
officials and military
personnel have access to and that to at
the highest level
so elon musk is not capable of nuking
the poles of mars he doesn't
have access to nuclear weapons if he can
convince people with governments to do
it then maybe it can happen but i think
he's just
being being humorous he's just making a
joke
i don't think it's a good idea because
of the radiation fallout if you
what what would nuking the poles of mars
achieve it would
basically cause the ice on the poles to
melt
and if you basically produce a
sufficient
quantity of heat from these nuclear
explosion then you could basically
recreate a sort of wet environment on
mass
or on mars which could perhaps trigger
back a spurt of growth of life and it
could change the atmosphere etc so it's
basically
a quick and dirty way of terraforming
the planet it is not a good idea because
of the
radiation fallout which would basically
contaminate the whole planet and the
entire atmosphere
because you would need a great deal of
nuclear energy
of you will need a great number of
nuclear bombs in order to achieve that
that result of making the whole planet
wet again and of melting the entire
quantum of ice on the two poles so it's
not a good idea that's not the way to do
do this do the terraforming of any
planet
it would have it's it's something that
you that you can't really control
right it would have lots of unintended
consequences you can game it all
and you can fly basically predict
roughly
what the effect would be but if you if
humanity is serious about making mars a
second home
in the long term future then nuking the
planet is
definitely not a good good idea good way
of doing that
so i think it's just humor but it's not
a good idea
so a related question by akash can we
really terraform
mars how are we going to get oxygen
water
plants and the ecosystem in a desolate
place like that
and how can we survive the cosmic
radiation without any ozone layer and
an atmosphere very good questions so
let's understand what mars is like
mars is a smaller planet its diameter is
maybe
half that of the earth its gravity is
about 38
of the earth so if somebody weighs 100
kilograms on earth
they would weigh 38 kilograms on mars
the atmosphere is basically 100
that of the earth roughly yeah mars
doesn't have a magnetic field which
means that there is
there is no way to stop the cosmic rays
in the solar wind
from bombarding the planet which means
that it would be
a very hazardous play a place for uh for
humans to be in
it would basically expose you to a great
deal of
of solar and cosmic radiation which is
very detrimental to human life
right and yeah there's the atmosphere is
very tenuous
compared to that of the earth there is
no ozone layer etc
so how do you terraform a planet like
that
firstly let's understand that in order
to terraform a planet
you need to be approximately a kardashev
type one civilization
which we are not we are nowhere near
being a kardashev type one civilization
we are not able to terraform our own
planet
we are not in control of the climate
change we are not able to stop that or
prevent that
we are not able to stop the pollution of
our oceans and so on and so forth
so we are not in control of what's
happening on the planet on our own home
planet uh
it's an out of control reaction or
process
so we are nowhere near being a kardashev
type one civilization and in order to
terraform a different planet
we would need that technological
capability
so assuming hypothetically that in the
future we
start reaching that stage maybe 0.8.9
kardashev
on the kardashev scale then how would we
go about
terraforming a planet like mars the
first thing is we need to give it
a good amount of atmosphere and an
atmosphere that's
that's comparable to that of our planet
here we want the right
mix of gases as well we need oxygen
first of all we also need
gas like nitrogen so we need to
give mars an atmosphere similar to that
of the earth
so it would have to be a hundred times
denser
uh more more more voluminous than the
atmosphere that we have in mars right
now
and we would need see right now the
temperature in mars is about
minus 60 or something degrees celsius
which is too cold for
for life as we know it some kind of life
can survive
in that temperature but it's not ideal
for human beings
the average temperature on earth is
about i don't know 14 20
something like that degrees celsius
centigrade
so we want the temperature to go above
zero at least
yeah so we need to bring about a number
of changes there we can't do anything
about the gravity of the planet which is
about a third of what we have here but
we can change the other
aspects and parameters of the planet so
one way of of warming the planet is to
uh surround the planet with orbiting
mirrors
that would focus more of the solar uh
light
and radiation on this surface of the
planet and that would heat up the planet
considerably and we can depending on the
number of mirrors in the
in the surface area total surface area
of the of the mirrors
we can basically if we are able to
achieve the technology then
we can possibly control and and the
and determine what is the specific
temperature we want to achieve
on the planet so that is one idea
orbiting mirrors around the planet maybe
a ring or several rings of mirrors
or mirrors in a hemispherical shape or
any such
or the best optimized shape to achieve
the desired effect
so for that we would need to build and
create the technology we still don't
have the technology to do that
but hypothetically theoretically it's
definitely possible
so that is one way to warm the planet
warming the planet would
basically reach the state of running
water because we know there's plenty of
water on mars
below the surface it's all frozen there
is a little bit of running water from
time to time
that that is observed and there's a
great deal of water at the poles
on the surface so by warming the planet
you would make it a wet planet
and then you would do certain things to
uh to create
a gaseous atmosphere as well
so there are a number of tactics you can
use and then how do you get oxygen water
plants you would need certain kinds of
chemical reactions
there's a lot of carbon dioxide on mars
if you grow plants there they would
release oxygen
and over the long term over the long run
maybe you would be able to produce
oxygen there
that's one idea the problem one of the
problems is that the soil of
mars is reasonably toxic it contains
certain perchlorates and other chemicals
that
are not that are toxic to life even
plant life so that is another problem
that we would have to overcome
so there's a lot of challenges right now
that we have
we would have to address each of these
issues one by one
and only when all these issues are
addressed will be will we be able to
terraform the planet and make it livable
for humanity in the long run in some
in some ways we can make it similar to
earth so this is all in the realm of
science fiction today we don't have
anything near the technology
as of today we can't even reach mars as
of as of today
maybe in a decades time or so we do have
the technology now to send people there
but we need to be able to send them and
bring them back safely
right now there's a reasonable amount of
risk involved
so this is all in the future maybe a
hundred years from today or
or approximately something like that
but it is possible it's definitely
possible a number of challenges need to
be overcome but
these are potentially
problems that we can actually solve
as they take as our technological
capabilities evolve and
as we come closer to the status of a
type one civilization
okay meenakshi asks what does borrowing
energy from space time mean so this is
in the context of quantum field theory
quantum field theory says that
the entire world is an illusion whatever
we see the entire world is made up of
fields and particles themselves are
local manifestations
local manifestations of these fields so
you have 17 different fields
that permeate the universe it's just one
field across the entire universe
and particles are local uh
manifestations of these fields
and it also says that the vacuum
of space itself is an illusion it is
full of uh
it's full of particle anti-particle
pairs
that are coming in and out of existence
at all times so it's extremely energetic
right so it is in this context that one
talks about the
this idea of borrowing energy from
space-time
so what it means is that uh the vacuum
of space is teaming with particle
anti-particle pairs
so a particle an anti-particle pair is
formed
out of the vacuum of space time and it
is formed and it very quickly
uh annihilates itself so it gives the
energy back to space-time
so isn't this something that violates
the conservation of energy right that's
the question
because uh you can't just borrow energy
from nowhere
energy has to be the the conservation of
energy has to be
respected so there is one loophole
called the heisenberg uncertainty
principle
so there is one formulation of this
principle that is the energy time
formulation
it basically says that energy the
uncertainty in energy and the
uncertainty
and time are inversely proportional to
each other
so the greater the uncertainty in energy
the smaller is the uncertainty in time
and the greater the uncertainty in time
the smaller the uncertainty and energy
which essentially i know it sounds like
gobbledygook but it essentially tells
you
that you can borrow energy
from vacuum as long as you give it back
within the time frame the time window
that heisenberg's uncertainty principle
gives you so that's what happens these
are all
virtual particle anti-particle pairs
these are these are
these form and annihilate each other too
quickly to be actually observed
but you can observe their indirect
effects and these experiments have been
done so it actually
is true there are such
particle anti-particle pairs being
formed and
destroyed all the time in vacuum
so basically you are borrowing energy
from the vacuum
and giving it back within the time
window
that is that that heisenberg uncertainty
heisenberg's uncertainty principle
gives you and that is a loophole that is
exploited
that that nature exploits in this manner
so you take energy and you give it back
in a very short period of time
before you violate the uncertainty
principle that's all it is basically
that's the best way to look at it so
that's how
vacuum itself has a great deal of energy
and it's
it's teeming with particle anti-particle
pairs
and that is one of the things that we
find in quantum field theory which is
the
most successful theory of the ultra
microscopic
universe that we have as of today
lena asks what is the fermi paradox
the fermi paradox can be stated in one
single sentence
where are all aliens so the thing is uh
the universe is immense
we have maybe maybe a trillion galaxies
or a hundred billion galaxies
or something approximately and
and if our home galaxy the milky way is
a typical galaxy
then it has approximately 100 billion
stars
right and we now know that most stars
have planets
so called exoplanets we have found
exoplanets in most of the stars that we
have been studying
so it looks like planets are very common
and if we total if we add up the number
of stars in the universe
it's a it's a very very large number uh
trillion multiplied by 100 billion a
trillion
is uh if you multiply 100 billion which
has
14 zeros a billion has nine zeros right
million billion yeah so it's eleven
zeros times eleven zeros
that's 22 zeros and if each star has
just one planet then you have 10 raised
to 22 planets
one with 22 zeros behind it in the
entire universe
that's the number of planets you have
now let's say
0.1 percent of them are in the habitable
zone of their stars where water can be
can flow as a liquid then still you have
10 raised to 20
or so planets in the habitable zone
so there are so many planets out there
in the universe in the habitable zone
then there should be then there should
be intelligent life out there it should
be pretty common right
and and yet we don't see any signs of
intelligent life in the world
we have never detected any transmission
or any any tilting sign
telltale sign that indicates that some
something artificial
is at work there something that
indicates uh
an intelligence an intelligent
intelligent life behind it
so we have thus far found no signal that
is
unequivocally proven to be a signal from
a different civilization
and therefore it appears to us that we
are all alone in the universe as an
intelligent life form as an intelligent
species
and even if there is microscopic or
microbial life out there it doesn't look
like there is any intelligent life out
there
so that is the paradox even though there
are so many galaxies
so many stars so many planets and yet we
don't find any
evidence of intelligent life there is
not one signal we have received
that is the fermi paradox and
there are a number of theories that seek
to explain
why it is so maybe space is so vast
that it is difficult to find signals
from other
species maybe intelligent life is more
intelligent than us and it doesn't want
to be
found maybe it doesn't just beam out
signals into space in all directions
maybe it conserves its its energy and
uses energy
very effective effectively efficiently
so that there are no
wasted transmissions that's another
possibility or maybe it's so advanced
because we don't even know how to detect
it
so these are possibilities or maybe we
are truly alone in the universe which is
frightening
to some people well so so these are
various possibilities these are various
theories and speculations we still don't
know what is uh
what really is out there is there
intelligent life or are we truly alone
so so that is the paradox where are all
the intelligent aliens
right so as of today we don't have
answers we are still seeking answers we
have these radio telescopes
in the seti seti project that's that
seeks that listens
to the universe for science of some
intelligent life etc
i think as our technology gets better
and better we will
i think we'll get a better understanding
of what really is out there
there are some people who believe that
we will make our first contact with
intelligent
alien civilizations within this century
some people believe they're already here
so as of today we don't know there is no
evidence uh
100 percent uh proven evidence
so that is a paradox where are all the
aliens
okay gaurangi asks can you put a light
on the properties of wimps
weakly interactive interacting massive
particles so the wimp
is one of the possible proposed
solutions to the dark matter problem
a weakly interacting massive particle is
a hypothetical
particle that interacts
via gravity and wire either the weak
nuclear force
or some other weak force that we don't
know of
so that's what it is it's a hypothetical
particle it's been proposed
to try and solve the question of
what is dark matter so there are models
in which you have
wimps clouds of whims high loss of wimps
or or maybe whims that uh
that permeate the world and we still
don't don't we are not able to detect
them
so it's one of the class of hypothetical
objects that seeks to
hypothetical particles that seeks to
uh try and answer the riddle of what
dark matter is
so there there is a whole bunch of
theories and and proposed particles some
exotics are not so exotic
that uh try to account for what dark
matter is as of today we have
no idea what dark matter is and the wimp
theory is one of the mainstream theories
but it's still
like all other theories not proven there
are whims there are axions there are
uh machos and many other
such particles maybe black holes
primordial black holes or primordial
black hole binaries
or even neutrinos could be anything
as of today we don't know what it is
it's mostly most likely cold
dark matter which means it doesn't it's
it's slow moving dark matter
but it's the so the wimp is one of these
hypothetical
particles that has been proposed to try
and solve the riddle of dark matter
it's a hypothetical particle it's never
been observed we have no
experimental evidence or detection of
these particles but it's still one of
the theories that is taken
seriously and it's one of a number of
theories
that is taken seriously in the hunt for
dark matter
sumit asks please explain something
about the dark side of the moon
so the earth and the moon are tidally
locked which means that they rotate in
such a manner that we can only see
the same side of the moon at all times
we can never see the other
other side of the moon it was not so in
the past in the past the two planets
where
the the planet and the moon were
rotating at different speeds but over
time they got tidally locked that's what
happens
uh and so we see only one side of the
moon and therefore for
the entirety of our existence as a
species
the past two three million years we have
only seen one
side of our moon and we we have always
been wondering what's on the other side
if there's any
so in the past people we don't know that
the moon is is spherical
but once we realize it is spherical we
were all curious about what is on the
other side
so the other side is now well known we
have taken photographs we have spent
space
sent spacecraft in orbit around the moon
and there are
very good high resolution images of the
other side of the moon
it's different from what we see on the
near side
of the moon there are different craters
but it's more or less the same kind of
surface
so there is nothing special about the
other side it's just that we
don't get to see it but now you can look
it up online you will see
photographs of the dark side so uh
one of the things good one of the
interesting things about the dark side
is if
if you are on the far side of the moon
then it is
a place where you have absolutely
complete radio silence
if you are on the near side of the moon
you are inundated with radio signals and
other transmissions from the earth
we are an extremely noisy species where
transmissions go out in all directions
in space
we are not efficient enough to conserve
those trans transmissions and
direct them only on the planet on the
surface of the planet
so the earth's uh surrounding area is a
very
noisy region lots of it's you're
constantly bombarded with radio
transmissions
and other transmissions throughout the
electromagnetic spectrum
all originating from human activity on
the surface of the planet
so if you are on the far side of the
moon you are shielded from that
and therefore it's a great place to do
astrophysical
experiments it's a great place for uh
for
for ex for example searching for
extraterrestrial
radio transmissions and for doing other
experiments which
would not be disturbed by the
electromagnetic
noise that is emanating from our planet
so that's why it's a great place on
which to keep on which to place
scientific instrumentation and do
various experiments so that is one of
the interesting things about the
about the far side of the moon it's not
dark it's just far
it also receives as much sunlight as the
side that we do see so it's not dark
it's just that
it's one of the popular ways of of
of terming it so it's the far side of
the moon
and uh recently uh the chinese have sent
a robotic spacecraft over there a
robotic lander it's still active as we
speak right now
and hopefully india also sends something
there once we get our chandrayaan-3
program moving the chandrayaan-3 program
will be
targeting the south pole region of the
moon on the near side
but eventually i hope we become
ambitious enough to send
future spacecraft on the far side
and get our own images and other things
from that from that side of the moon
so that's all it is it's nothing special
it's just the side that we don't see
but it's very much like the
near side the only special thing is that
there is complete
silence on the electromagnetic spectrum
as of today
okay next question
akash asks is there a limit to
technology could there be some day
where we can't proceed further beyond a
certain point because of the laws of the
universe
yes there are things that the laws of
the universe don't allow and therefore
we cannot violate those
those are just hard coded in the
universe you simply can't
uh you simply can't violate the
fundamental laws of the
of the universe the actual limit to
technology
is our own intelligence limit right we
as a species
have a certain maximum intelligence and
we simply can't go beyond that
and therefore because of the limit of
our intelligence
there will be certain things that we
will most likely never understand
until we evolve further and
possibly become more intelligent than
what we are today
so we tend to think of ourselves as the
most intelligent thing in the universe
and therefore we can understand
everything i think on the larger scale
of the
of the universe there could be possibly
other beings
other civilizations other species on
other
stars galaxies who would be who could
possibly be
way more intelligent than us and the
the intelligence um
the the way to see the difference in
intelligence would be
the way we see a dog or a cat you know
or maybe an insect
i mean there's no comparison of the kind
of intelligence we have
compared to the kind of intelligence
butterfly has right
so there could possibly be such
civilizations and species who are so
intelligent that we are essentially like
butterflies to them
and therefore their understanding of the
universe would be
many orders of magnitude better than
ours and therefore the technology
that the kind of technology they develop
they would be able to develop
would be far beyond anything we can even
imagine
so i think the real limit to technology
is the limit of our intelligence it's
not the laws of the universe
of course the laws of the universe will
not allow you to do magic
you know so yeah there are things that
the universe doesn't allow you to do
but the real limit to technology is the
human intelligence
and the limits of human intelligence
itself
so i think that is a real limit and
that's why we cannot proceed beyond a
certain point definitely there is a
point beyond
humanity even if it achieves its full
potential today
it still can't go beyond a certain point
and it is not because of the laws of the
universe it's because of our own
limitations of our intelligence
okay gaurangi asks why are we trying to
set up
colonies on mars why not the moon which
is much closer as you say
or is terra forming the moon more
difficult than mars
well that's a very good question i'm
sure lots of people have this question
because the moon is right next door we
can go there in like
a couple of days less than a week's time
we can reach there
with the current technology that we have
uh so yeah good question why don't we
terraform the moon
the thing is this uh when you are
talking about
moving to a different location to a
different planet
you want it to be as close to the earth
not as close but as much earth like as
possible
so you want it to be similar in size
you want it to have a similar kind of
atmosphere to start off with
so before you terraform a planet you
look at
a number of candidates and you take the
one that is the closest in in
in its nature and appearance to the
earth
so it should be similar sized and all
that
so the closest candidate we have is mars
actually venus is almost the same size
as the earth
right but its atmosphere is is an
absolute hell
it's about 300 times larger greater than
the earth the atmospheric pressure is i
think
300 times or so greater than what we
have on the earth
and the atmospheric composition is
absolute hell you have
sulfur dioxide sulfuric acid rain
and and lightening and thunder and all
that right so
it's a terrible place to even think of
settling in
and it's almost impossible to terraform
mars on the other hand
even though it's smaller than our planet
has certain conditions that are similar
to that of earth for example it's days
about 24 hours long
it did have running water liquid water
in the past
it may even have had life in the past
and
it's uh the temperature is low of course
but those things can be changed
the moon on the other hand doesn't have
an atmosphere it at all
its gravity is about 1 6 of that of the
earth so if you weigh 100 kilos on earth
you would weigh 1
6 of that on the moon and
that is not a good it's not conducive to
human health you know
we need gravity to in order to remain
healthy people who go out in space and
spend a year in orbit
they essentially become extremely weak
their bones become more brittle
and there are effects on the
cardiovascular system and all that
which are which so basically lower
gravity is not good for human health
and therefore mars is a much better
candidate from that perspective than the
moon
because its gravity is about 38
of that of the earth and it already has
an atmosphere
which we can augment hopefully the moon
doesn't have an atmosphere
it does have a very tenuous wispy quasi
atmosphere which is
basically almost the same as vacuum
so that these are the reasons why mars
is a better candidate even the
soil of the moon is is not it's
it's quite i don't think it's very
conducive to growing plants and all that
so the main reason is the moon is too
small it's gravity is too weak
secondly it doesn't have an atmosphere
it is almost impossible
it is completely impossible to give it
an artificial atmosphere because
its gravity gravity is so weak that even
if you give it an artificial atmosphere
the atmosphere will slowly leak away in
a reasonably
short period of time so it has to be a
massive planet more massive than the
moon
and these are the reasons why the mars
is a much better
candidate for terraforming and for
long-term future human habitation than
the moon even though the moon is so
close by
so these are the reasons why we prefer
why everyone prefers
mars as opposed to the moon
right i think that's the end of all the
all these questions so let me take a
look at what questions you are asking me
and i'll take a few
live chat questions
one of the reasons for not forming
colonies on the moon
moon has no atmosphere yes correct
that's
uh yeah i agree that's what i was saying
good question if singularities and
mathematical equations are considered to
be
yeah any incomplete me it means that the
theory isn't correct
is it entirely correct so is it possible
that the big bang didn't start from a
singularity
and if yes then why do we stay started
from it
we say the big bang started from a
singularity because that's what general
relativity tells us
right but like you said singularities
like you point out over here
singularities are essentially a flaw in
the equations it's not a real
singularity
it a singularity in in your theory
indicates that the theory is not
complete
there is something you need to do
further which will reveal better and
more complete laws of nature
and therefore yes it is possible indeed
that the big bank didn't
start from a singularity maybe there was
something else maybe there was a big
bounce
so there is the theory called loop
quantum gravity which says that
in which in this theory in loop quantum
gravity
space time itself is quantized and the
minimum
volume of space time is 10 to the minus
cubic cubic meter
so yeah in that case the universe would
not have had a big bang it would have a
big bounce
so the minimum volume possible is 10 to
the minus 99
cubic meters or cubic centimeters yeah
so so in so in this theory yes the big
bank did not start from a singularity it
started
started from that minimum minimum
quantum
of volume of space time so yeah like
you're saying
it is very much possible we need to
find a better theory we need to uh
improve
the theory of general relativity and
hopefully
quantize it and find the
true quantum theory of gravitation in
which case
we most likely won't have singularities
and we will have a better understanding
of what the
so-called big bang was like so that's a
great question
okay sagar asks will i be wrong if i say
something is a non-living thing because
at the atomic level
everything may is made of chemical
compositions
and if yes then please comment about
consciousness
so at the atomic level everything is
atoms
molecules electrons protons neutrons all
that subatomic level
so everything is atoms and at the higher
level molecular level you have
chemicals and then you have biochemistry
the biochemistry of life you have carbon
compounds
you have amino acids that are the
building blocks of life etc
so we don't exactly have
a clear definition of the boundary
between living
and non-living right
so biochemistry is all about the
chemistry of life
life seems to emerge out of complex
chemistry
the kind of life we have on our planet
emerges out of the
biochemistry of carbon compounds
so it is believed that life emerged in
the primordial earth
because of the kind of conditions we had
on the planet and the kind of
chemical uh composition we had on the
cam
on the planet but we don't exactly know
what is the dividing life between
non-living and living most likely living
is a unicellular organism
with a single cell maybe a nucleus
within it and maybe
dna in the nucleus so we don't have a
clear definition
of the dividing line between living and
non-living
so uh so since we don't have a clear
definition we can't really say what is
living what what is non-living
we know that we are living we know that
all life on planet is living when we see
life
we can say yeah this is life but there
are certain things that are on the
dividing line between
living and non-living beings for example
viruses
viruses exhibit properties that are of
living beings
they also exhibit properties that are of
non-living
substances so viruses are are
are on the dividing line they do have
dna they do replicate but they don't
uh there are certain things that like
they don't uh
react to the environment they don't uh
maintain
a certain kind of composition within
within their
living cells and all that so there are
there are certain things about viruses
that
categorize them between the living and
non-living boundary
so so it's a good question and it's a
question that's a matter of debate right
now
at the atomic level there is no life of
course at the chemical
molecular level it's all chemistry there
is no life it's only when you talk about
biochemistry
the chemistry that occurs within living
beings that you're talking about life to
some extent
so is everything a non-living thing no
we have life but we also have atoms we
also have chemicals
so you're talking about classification
and nomenclature essentially that's the
question that's what the question is
so it's it's kind of vague that's where
that's why biology and chemistry biology
especially is not a very exact science
the only exact science is physics
chemistry emerges out of physics and
biology emerges out of chemistry
so you are talking in terms of more
accurate representations of nature when
you only talk about physics
chemistry is also reasonably accurate
biology is a little little vague
so it would not be correct to say that
everything is non-living
we are made up of non-living components
but there is definitely life within us
and we don't have a very clear
definition of life about consciousness
well consciousness is another big
mystery
is one of one of the mysteries that is
now closely
tied to the quantum world because
consciousness seems possibly to have
some kind of
role to play in the observer effect and
in manifesting certain things and all
that right
so we don't have a clear definition of
consciousness we don't have the biggest
definition of what consciousness is all
we can say is that we are conscious and
other living beings are conscious
but we don't have a definition a proper
unambiguous scientific definition
of what consciousness is so that's
another matter of great debate right now
it is now consciousness is now beginning
to enter the realm of science
until now it's been in the realm of
philosophy and spirituality which is
separate from science it is not
scientific but today
because of quantum mechanics we are
increasingly trying to understand the
phenomenon of consciousness
is it an emergent phenomenon or is it
something else
uh many scientists would tell you that
that
that consciousness emerges out of the
chemical re
out of the biochemical reactions within
the brain so that is one possibility
other scientists would strongly disagree
with that
so as of now until we can clearly define
consciousness we can't really start
having a proper scientific discussion
about this
so it's a matter of great discussion and
debate right now but it's not
firmly entered the realm of science
it's still quite hazy and vague so good
question sir
okay akashic record so i don't know what
akashic records are this is something in
the realm of spirituality we're talking
about science today
i am not saying i'm not trying to make
fun of spirituality
i am not discounting spirituality or
philosophy
i'm just saying these are separate
things okay so a scientist
what is science and what is the
difference between science and
philosophy
or science and spirituality we have to
understand this clearly
science deals with the observable
universe and material objects
only that that is the firm
limitation of science only material
objects
and only the observable universe nothing
beyond that
so that is science that's what it deals
with philosophy
deals with the material universe and
observable objects
but it also deals with non-observable
objects and phenomena it deals with
things like
right and wrong it deals with questions
of morality and
ethics and of non-physical
objects like the soul and consciousness
right so these are things that are
non-observable
non-physical by definition the soul is
non-physical it's not observable right
we can't see it
we can't measure it therefore it is in
the realm of philosophy
not in the realm of science it doesn't
mean it may not exist
but as a scientist i can't see it i
can't detect it i can't measure it
and therefore i will not talk about it
that's what is the attitude of
scientists as it should be
although if you start mixing things up
then you're no longer in one place or
the other
and similarly the akashic records is
something that is in the realm of
spirituality
which is again a higher it's it's again
something that is
that is something similar to philosophy
i think i'll have to do a separate
session in which i
i uh define these things very clearly i
will do that
but once again spirituality is not part
of science
right so you can't say that because it
is there in spirituality spiritual
spirituality therefore it should be
scientifically valid no
science only deals with physical objects
and observable phenomena that's all it
is
that is a limitation of science
it doesn't mean these other things don't
exist it doesn't mean we should make fun
of them
maybe they do exist and maybe our
science isn't evolved enough
like i have been emphasizing repeatedly
we know very little about the universe
our science is very rudimentary
we don't know about how the universe
started we don't know
what created the universe what impelled
the so-called big bang we don't know so
many things
95 of the universe is dark therefore
science has a great deal of limitations
our understanding of sciences is even
more limited
and therefore if one were to evolve and
become more intelligent in the future
then maybe some of the things that we
speak about in spirituality
in philosophy may in the future possibly
perhaps someday
come into the realm of science if we can
observe
and quantify and measure these phenomena
as of today
it is spirituality it is philosophy it
is not science
and therefore philosophical and
spiritual
concepts cannot give us answers
in the physical world in the realm of
the physical sciences
so i hope that clarifies the difference
between science and philosophy
i think it is wrong for scientists to
make fun of spirituality or philosophy
that is that is the
sign of a of a narrow and closed mind
but
as a scientist you have to deal with the
physical and observable universe only
and many scientists have spiritual and
philosophical opinions and beliefs
but as a scientist you don't write
papers on spirituality and physics
you write papers on science only so i
hope that
clarifies this matter
okay one more question
okay so after a person died six grams or
something like that body loses weight my
thoughts well
when a person dies when any any living
being
dies their physical nature changes the
biochemical processes
processes that sustain life stop
they may lose some some some
water mass in the form of gas
and many changes happen in the body so
yes the weight will change within a few
hours
maybe within a few minutes etc it
indicates
a complete change in the biochemistry of
that physical body that's all
it indicates it doesn't mean anything
else some people try to say that the
soul has left the body and that's why
the body is lighter
well where is the evidence show me the
soul that left the body
i am not saying there is no soul there
may be a soul
however it is not physically measurable
or quantifiable
if there is a loss in the weight of a
body
a change in the weight of the body it
can be very easily explained by the
altered biochemistry of that physical
body
and therefore it does not prove the
existence of a soul
i am not saying again that it means the
soul doesn't exist i am not of that
opinion
i am saying that it is a matter of
philosophy and spirituality
it's not a matter of physics and science
i i hope that helps you better
understand
the difference between science and
philosophy both are valid
valid and and important
aspects of the intellectual pursuits of
humanity
but these are separate aspects you we
cannot
start merging the two
shall i take one more okay let me take
one final question
what is the relationship between area 51
and
aliens well we don't know
it's a secret location where nobody is
ever allowed inside
right the media isn't allowed inside
civilians aren't allowed inside
uh it's a very highly secure location
it's where the u.s military essentially
carries out tests of secret futuristic
technology technology that is not
revealed for many decades
and that's why people believe that
aliens uh there is some alien connection
or something maybe there are some alien
spacecraft etc that are being tested
over there is it possible
well it's not impossible i cannot prove
it's not happening so maybe it's
happening but
i think the probability is is on the
lower side
that there is actual alien technology
there but i am not discounting the
possibility
but as you know i don't have proof my
opinion is there is a small possibility
that maybe there is something like that
but most likely it's just a highly
secure and secret location
where the latest technology is being
developed and when they fly these
futuristic aircraft in the night sky it
may look like
alien spacecraft because you don't know
what actually it is
right so when they were testing the uh
so-called
stealth bomber that bomber has a very
alien shape doesn't it
it's a flying wing design and if
somebody sees it in the night sky
with lights lights on it would look very
much like an alien spacecraft
so that's why that's one of the possible
reasons why it is associated with
aliens and all that and there are
persistent claims that they have alien
technology there etc
so i think maybe maybe it's possible i
don't have evidence
i have an open mind so i think maybe
it's true
right my friends uh this brings us to an
end
for this session great questions keep
them coming
we're gonna do it again next week so
thank you all for participating thank
you for listening watching
and i will see you in the next session
thank you very much good night good day
bye